A Finding Aid to the Katherine Gauss Jackson papers, 1919-1974, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Katherine Gauss Jackson papers
1919-1974
Archives of American Art
Jackson, Katherine Gauss
AAA.jackkath
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of Katherine Gauss Jackson measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1919 to 1974. The bulk of the collection consists of letters from Alfred H. Barr, Jr. to Katherine Gauss Jackson during the 1920s while they were studying at Princeton University and Smith College, respectively. Also found is scattered material relating to Barr including an outline on Russian music, a photograph, notes on modern art, and printed material concerning Barr's 70th birthday celebration.
Biographical / Historical
Katherine Gauss Jackson (1904-1975) was a writer and magazine editor in North Egremont, Massachusetts, and the New York City area. She was the editor of fiction for Harper's. Alfred Hamilton Barr, Jr. (1902-1981) was the director of the Museum of Modern Art in New York City. Barr and Jackson had known each other in Greensboro, Vermont, where their families had summer homes. Barr attended Princeton University while Jackson's father was Dean of the College.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Katherine Gauss Jackson measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1919 to 1974. The bulk of the collection consists of letters from Alfred H. Barr, Jr. to Katherine Gauss Jackson during the 1920s while they were studying at Princeton University and Smith College, respectively. Also found is scattered material relating to Barr including an outline on Russian music, a photograph, notes on modern art, and printed material concerning Barr's 70th birthday celebration.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were received from the donor, Katharine Gauss Jackson, through Russell Lynes.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reel 1115 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York; Editors -- Massachusetts -- North Egremont; Authors -- Massachusetts -- North Egremont; Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1902-1981
- Alfred H. Barr Papers, 1919-1974; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes materials sent to Katherine Gauss Jackson over the course of her long friendship with Alfred H. Barr, Jr. General material includes a "bluff sheet" outlining Russian classical music; a photograph of Barr with others from 1923; notes on postcards commenting on modern art; and clippings and an invitation for Barr's 70th birthday celebration. Barr's letters to Jackson are personal and are largely written during his time at Princeton University and while she was studying at Smith College in the 1920s. The letters discuss their friendship and connection, friends, classes, and social events. Also found are scattered letters from Margaret Scolari Barr to Jackson.
  - General, 1923-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1919-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Letters, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Letters, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1928-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1933-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)